I would like to show you how
أريد أن أريكم كيف
architecture has helped
ساعد المهندسيين المعماريين
to change the life of my community
في تغيير الحياة في مجتمعي
and has opened opportunities to hope.
وفتحوا الفرص للأمل
I am a native of Burkina Faso.
أنا من بوركينا فاسو في الأصل
According to the World Bank, Burkina Faso
إعتماداً على البنك الدولي, بوركينا فاسو
is one of the poorest countries in the world,
هي واحدة من أفقر الدول في العالم
but what does it look like
لكن ماذا يشبه
to grow up in a place like that?
أن تتربى في مكان كهذا
I am an example of that.
أنا مثال لهذا
I was born in a little village called Gando.
انا ولدت في قرية صغيرة تسمى غاندو
In Gando, there was no electricity,
في غاندو, كان لا يوجد كهرباء
no access to clean drinking water, and no school.
لا توجد امكانية للحصول على ماء نظيف, ولا يوجد مدارس
But my father wanted me
لكن ابي ارادني
to learn how to read and write.
ان اتعلم القراءة والكتابة
For this reason, I had to leave my family
لهذا السبب, كان علي ان اترك العائلة
when I was seven and to stay in a city
عندما كنت في السابعة وان اسكن في مدينة
far away from my village
بعيدة عن قريتي
with no contact with my family.
بدون وسيلة للاتصال بعائلتي
In this place I sat
في هذا المكان انا بقيت
in a class like that
في فصل كهذا
with more than 150 other kids,
مع أكثر من 150 طالب آخر
and for six years.
ولست سنوات
In this time, it just happened to me to come to school
في هذا الوقت, حصلت معي أن أدرس في هذه المدرسة
to realize that my classmate died.
لألاحظ أن زملائي يموتون.
Today, not so much has changed.
اليوم, لم يتغير الكثير
There is still no electricity in my village.
لا زال لا يوجد هناك كهرباء في قريتي
People still are dying in Burkina Faso,
الناس لازالوا يموتون في بوركينا فاسو
and access to clean drinking water
والحصول على ماء نظيف للشرب
is still a big problem.
لازالت مشكلة كبيرة
I had luck. I was lucky, because this is a fact of life
كان لدي حظ, كنت محظوظاً.. لأن هذه حقيقة الحياة
when you grow up in a place like that.
عندما تتربى في مكان كهذا
But I was lucky.
لكن أنا كنت محظوظاً
I had a scholarship.
حصلت على برنامج دراسي
I could go to Germany to study.
بإمكاني أن اذهب لألمانيا لأدرس
So now, I suppose,
الأن, أنا أفترض
I don't need to explain to you how great a privilege
أني لا أحتاج أن اشرح لكم كم هي ميزة عظيمة
it is for me to be standing before you today.
لي أن أقف أمامكم اليوم.
From Gando, my home village in Burkina Faso,
من غاندو, قريتي في بوركينا فاسو
to Berlin in Germany to become an architect
إلى برلين في ألمانيا لأصبح مهندس معماري
is a big, big step.
هي خطوة كبيرة جداً جداً
But what to do with this privilege?
لكن ماهو العمل بهذه الميزة؟
Since I was a student, I wanted to open up
عندما كنت طالب, أردت أن افتح
better opportunities to other kids in Gando.
فرص أفضل للأطفال الآخرين في غاندو
I just wanted to use my skills and build a school.
أردت فقط أن أستخدم مهاراتي لأبني مدرسة
But how do you do it when you're still a student
لكن كيف تفعل ذلك وأنت لازلت طالب
and you don't have money?
ولاتملك مال
Oh yes, I started to make drawings
حسناً, بدأت بعمل رسمات
and asked for money.
وأقاضيها بمال
Fundraising was not an easy task.
جمع التبرعات ليست مهمة سهلة
I even asked my classmates
انا حتى سألت زملائي
to spend less money on coffee and cigarettes,
لصرف القليل من المال على القهوة والسجائر
but to sponsor my school project.
ودعم مشروع مدرستي
In real wonder, two years later,
بشكل عجيب جداً, بعد سنتين
I was able to collect 50,000 U.S. dollars.
أستطعت أن أجمع 50.000 دولار أمريكي
When I came home to Gando
عندما رجعت إلى غاندو
to bring the good news,
لأجلب لهم الخبر السعيد
my people were over the moon,
قومي وصلوا إلى القمر
but when they realized
لكن عندما لاحظوا
that I was planning to use clay,
أنني كنت أخطط أن استخدم الطين في البناء
they were shocked.
صدموا
"A clay building is not able to stand a rainy season,
"المبنى الطيني لا يمكن التحمل في موسم الأمطار
and Francis wants us to use it and build a school.
وفرانسس يريدنا أن نستخدمها في بناء مدرسة.
Is this the reason why he spent so much time
هل هذا هو السبب لماذا قضى وقتاً طويلاً
in Europe studying
للدراسة في اوروبا
instead of working in the field with us?"
بدلاً من العمل في الحقول معنا؟"
My people build all the time with clay,
قومي يبنون دائماً بالطين
but they don't see any innovation with mud.
لكنهم لا يرون أية ابتكار في الطين
So I had to convince everybody.
لذلك يجب علي ان اقنع الجميع
I started to speak with the community,
بدأت أتكلم مع المجتمع
and I could convince everybody,
واستطعت ان اقنع الجميع
and we could start to work.
وكان بإستطاعتنا أن نبدأ العمل
And the women, the men,
والنساء, والرجال
everybody from the village,
الجميع من القرية
was part of this building process.
كانوا جزء من عملية البناء
I was allowed to use even traditional techniques.
كان يسمح لي حتى بإستخدام الأساليب التقليدية
So clay floor for example,
الدور الطيني مثلاً
the young men come and stand like that, beating,
الرجال اليافعين جاءوا ووقفوا هكذا, يضربون
hours for hours,
ساعات وساعات
and then their mothers came,
بعد ذلك, جاءت أمهم
and they are beating in this position,
فأخذوا يضربون بهذه الطريقة
for hours, giving water and beating.
لساعات, يأخذون الماء ويضربون
And then the polishers come.
ثم جاء الملمعين
They start polishing it with a stone for hours.
بدأوا بالتلميع بحجر لساعات
And then you have this result,
ثم تحصل على هذه النتيجة
very fine, like a baby bottom.
جيد جداً, مثل مؤخرة طفل رضيع
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's not photoshopped. (Laughter)
ليست معدلة بالفوتوشوب.
This is the school, built with the community.
هذه المدرسة, بنيت عن طريق المجتمع
The walls are totally made out
الجدران صنعت تماماً
of compressed clay blocks from Gando.
من طوب الطين المضغوط من غاندو
The roof structure is made
بنية السقف مصنوعة
with cheap steel bars
من قضبان حديدية رخيصة
normally hiding inside concrete.
مختبئة عادة خلف الأسمنت
And the classroom, the ceiling is made
وقاعة الدراسة, السقف صنع
out of both of them used together.
من كلاهما بإستخدامهما مع بعضهما
In this school, there was a simple idea:
في هذه المدرسة, كانت هناك فكرة بسيطة
to create comfort in a classroom.
لخلق إرتياح في قاعة الدراسة
Don't forget, it can be 45 degrees in Burkina Faso,
لا تنسى, بالإمكان ان تكون 45 درجة في بوركينا فاسو
so with simple ventilation,
لذلك مع فتحة تهوية بسيطة
I wanted to make the classroom
أردت أن أجعل قاعة الدراسة
good for teaching and learning.
جيدة للتدريس والتعليم
And this is the project today,
وهذا المشروع اليوم
12 years old, still in best condition.
عمره 12 سنة, لازال في حالة ممتازة
And the kids, they love it.
والأطفال يحبونه
And for me and my community,
وبالنسبة لي ومجتمعي أيضاً
this project was a huge success.
المشروع كان نجاح هائل
It has opened up opportunities
فتح لنا الفرص
to do more projects in Gando.
لفعل المزيد من المشاريع في غاندو
So I could do a lot of projects,
بإمكاني أن أعمل الكثير من المشاريع
and here I am going to share with you
وانا هنا لأشارككم
only three of them.
ثلاثة منهم فقط
The first one is the school extension, of course.
الأول هو توسيع المدرسة, بالطبع
How do you explain drawings and engineering
كيف تشرح الرسمات والهندسة
to people who are neither able to read nor write?
لأشخاص ليس بإمكانهم القراءة ولا الكتابة
I started to build a prototype like that.
بدأت ببناء نموذج بدائي مثل هذا
The innovation was to build a clay vault.
الإبتكار كان بناء سرداب طيني
So then, I jumped on the top like that,
بعد ذلك, قفزت إلى الأعلى هكذا
with my team, and it works.
مع فريقي, ونجحت
The community is looking. It still works.
المجتمع يرى, لازالت تعمل
So we can build. (Laughter)
بإمكاننا البناء
And we kept building, and that is the result.
أستمرينا في البناء, وهذه هي النتيجة
The kids are happy, and they love it.
الأطفال سعداء, وأحبوها
The community is very proud. We made it.
المجتمع كان فخور جداً, نحن نجحنا
And even animals, like these donkeys,
حتى الحيوانات, مثل هذه الحمير
love our buildings.
أحبت مبانينا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The next project is the library in Gando.
المشروع التالي هو المكتبة في غاندو
And see now, we tried to introduce
وأنظر الأن, نحن حاولنا لتقديم
different ideas in our buildings,
أفكار مختلفة في مبانينا
but we often don't have so much material.
لكن غالباً نحن لا نملك الكثير من المواد
Something we have in Gando are clay pots.
الشيء الذي نملكه في غاندو هو جرار طينية
We wanted to use them to create openings.
أردنا أن نستخدمها لإنشاء بدايات
So we just bring them like you can see
فقط جلبناها كما بإمكانك ان ترى
to the building site.
لموقع البناء
we start cutting them,
بدأنا في قطعها
and then we place them on top of the roof
ثم وضعناها على أعلى السطح
before we pour the concrete,
قبل أن نصب الأسمنت
and you have this result.
وستحصل على هذه النتيجة
The openings are letting the hot air out
الفتحات تدع الهواء الحار يخرج
and light in.
والنور يدخل
Very simple.
بسيط جداً
My most recent project in Gando
مشروعي الجديد جداً في غاندو
is a high school project.
هو مشروع مدرسة ثانوية
I would like to share with you this.
أود أن أشارككم هذا
The innovation in this project
الإبتكار في هذا المشروع
is to cast mud like you cast concrete.
هو أن تصب الطين كما تصب الأسمنت
How do you cast mud?
كيف تصب الأسمنت؟
We start making a lot of mortars, like you can see,
بدأت بصناعة الكثير من الخلاطات, كما ترون
and when everything is ready,
وعندما كان كل شيء جاهز
when you know what is the best recipe
عندما تعرف ماهي الوصفة الأفضل
and the best form,
والنموذج الأفضل
you start working with the community.
تبدأ تعمل مع المجتمع
And sometimes I can leave.
أحياناً استطيع الذهاب
They will do it themselves.
وهم بإمكانهم العمل بإنفسهم
I came to speak to you like that.
جئت إليكم لأتحدث هكذا
Another factor in Gando is rain.
عامل آخر في غاندو هو المطر
When the rains come,
عندما يأتي المطر
we hurry up to protect our fragile walls
نسرع لنغطي جدراننا الهشة
against the rain.
ضد المطر
Don't confound with Christo and Jeanne-Claude.
لا تحتاروا مع كريستو وجان كلود
It is simply how we protect our walls.
هكذا بكل بساطة نحمي جدراننا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The rain in Burkina comes very fast,
المطر في بوركينا فاسو سريع جداً
and after that, you have floods
وبعد ذلك, ستحصل على الفيضان
everywhere in the country.
في كل مكان من الدولة
But for us, the rain is good.
لكن بالنسبة لنا, المطر جيد
It brings sand and gravel to the river
يجلب لنا التراب والحصى للنهر
we need to use to build.
التي نحتاج لأستخدامها في البناء
We just wait for the rain to go.
فقط ننتظر المطر ليذهب
We take the sand, we mix it with clay,
نأخذ التراب, ونخلطه بالطين
and we keep building.
ونستمر في البناء
That is it.
هكذا فقط.
The Gando project was always connected to training the people,
مشروع غاندو كان دائماً يربط بتدريب الناس
because I just wanted, one day
بسبب أني أردت فقط, في يوم ما
when I fall down and die,
عندما أسقط وأموت
that at least one person from Gando
هذا على الأقل شخص واحد من غاندو
keeps doing this work.
يستمر بعمل هذا العمل
But you will be surprised. I'm still alive.
لكنكم ستتفاجئون انا لازلت حي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And my people now can use their skills
وقومي الأن بإمكانهم يستخدمون مهاراتهم
to earn money themselves.
للحصول على المال لأنفسهم
Usually, for a young man from Gando to earn money,
عادة, للشباب الصغار من غاندو ليحصل على مال
you have to leave the country
يجب عليه ان يغادر الريف
to the city, sometimes leave the country
للمدينة, أحياناً يغادر البلاد
and some never come back,
وبعضهم لا يرجع أبداً
making the community weaker.
ليحول هذا المجتمع إلى أضعف
But now they can stay in the country
لكن الأن بإمكانهم ان يبقوا في البلاد
and work on different building sites
ويعملون في مواقع بناء مختلفة
and earn money to feed their family.
ويحصلون على مال ليطعمون به عائلتهم
There's a new quality in this work.
هناك جودة جديدة في هذا العمل
Yes, you know it.
نعم, أنت تعرفها
I have won a lot of awards through this work.
حصلت على الكثير من الجوائز خلال هذا العمل
For sure, it has opened opportunities.
بالتأكيد, فتحت الفرص
I have become myself known.
لقد أصبحت بنفسي معروف
But the reason why I do what I do
لكن السبب لماذا أفعل ما أقوم بفعله
is my community.
هو مجتمعي
When I was a kid,
عندما كنت طفلاً
I was going to school,
كنت أذهب إلى المدرسة
I was coming back every holiday to Gando.
كنت أرجع في كل عطلة إلى غاندو
By the end of every holidays,
عند انتهاء كل عطلة
I had to say goodbye to the community,
أضطر لأن أقول وداعاً لمجتمعي
going from one compound to another one.
أذهب من مجمع لآخر
All women in Gando will open their clothes like that
كل النساء سيفتحون ملابسهم هكذا
and give me the last penny.
ليعطوني آخر قرش
In my culture, this is a symbol of deep affection.
في حضارتي, هذا رمز للعاطفة العميقة
As a seven-year-old guy, I was impressed.
كشخص في السابعة من عمره, كنت معجب
I just asked my mother one day,
سألت أمي مرة
"Why do all these women love me so much?"
"لماذا هؤلاء النساء يحبوني جداً؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
She just answered,
هي فقط أجابت
"They are contributing to pay for your education
هم يساهمون ليدفعوا لتعليمك
hoping that you will be successful
آملين أنك ستكون ناجحاً
and one day come back and help
وستعود يوماً وتساعدهم
improve the quality of life of the community."
في تحسين جودة الحياة في المجتمع"
I hope now that I was able to make my community proud
آمل أني الأن استطيع أن أجعل مجتمعي فخوراً
through this work,
خلال هذا العمل
and I hope I was able to prove you the power
وآمل أني استطيع أن أثبت لكم القوة
of community,
في مجتمعي
and to show you that architecture
وأريكم ان الهندسة المعمارية
can be inspiring for communities
بإمكانها أن تكون محفزة للمجتمعات
to shape their own future.
لتشكيل مستقبلهم
Merci beaucoup. (Applause)
شكراً جزيلاً (بالفرنسية)
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
شكراً, شكراً , شكراً, شكراً
Thank you. Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً, شكراً